It had its own army of 260,000 men. ... It ruled over 150 million people. ... It was the first corporation too big to fail.
In the year sixteen-hundred, Queen Elizabeth the First signed a simple charter. It granted a monopoly on trade with the East Indies to a small group of London merchants. ... They called it the East India Company.
For a century, they traded spices and textiles. But trade wasn't enough. In 1757, at the Battle of Plassey, the company stopped being merchants... and became conquerors.
To protect their assets, the Company built a private military force. At its peak, this corporate army numbered two hundred and sixty thousand soldiers. ... Twice the size of the British army.
They seized control of Bengal, the richest province in India. The Company stripped the land of its wealth, transferring millions of pounds directly into the pockets of its shareholders.
But this unbridled greed came at a horrifying cost. ... In 1770, a massive famine struck Bengal. Instead of providing relief, the Company raised taxes.
Millions perished. Yet, the Company was nearly bankrupt from mismanagement and wars. To save their most prized asset, the British government stepped in with the world's first massive corporate bailout.
To dump the Company's surplus tea, Parliament passed the Tea Act. ... This desperate move to save a failing corporation directly triggered the Boston Tea Party, sparking the American Revolution.
Desperate for profits, the Company found a new, darker revenue stream. They grew opium in India and smuggled it into China, addicting millions to balance their ledgers.
The breaking point finally arrived in 1857. ... A massive rebellion erupted across India against the Company's brutal rule. The corporation had lost control of its empire.
The British Crown stepped in, stripping the East India Company of its powers. The beast was dead. It was formally dissolved, reduced to a mere historical footnote.
The East India Company showed the world the terrifying potential of unchecked corporate power. ... A lesson that, perhaps, we are still ignoring today. Subscribe to Shadow Empires.