In the winter of 1924, far from the public eye, a group of powerful industrialists quietly gathered in a smoke-filled room in Geneva, Switzerland. ... Representing the world's leading lighting conglomerates, these men were not there to celebrate innovation. ... Instead, they were planning a conspiracy that would secretly restrict global progress. ... Their objective was simple yet sinister: to intentionally design a lightbulb that would fail sooner, forcing consumers to buy more. It was the birth of planned obsolescence—a calculated sabotage of human engineering—and for decades, they got away with it completely.
To understand the magnitude of their betrayal, we must travel to a humble fire station in Livermore, California. ... Hanging from the ceiling is a small, hand-blown bulb known as the Centennial Light. ... It was manufactured by the Shelby Electric Company and has been burning continuously since the year 1901. For over a century, it has defied modern engineering, outliving the firemen who hung it, the building around it, and the very company that made it. ... It stands as living proof that we had the technology to make lightbulbs last forever—and that the industry deliberately chose to destroy it.
In the early days of electrification, durability was the ultimate selling point. ... Pioneers like Thomas Edison in America and Joseph Swan in Great Britain competed fiercely to engineer the most robust, long-lasting carbon filaments. ... The technology was advancing rapidly. By the early 1920s, lightbulbs could easily burn for over 2,500 hours without losing their brilliance. It was a golden age of engineering. But as the bulbs became more perfect, the manufacturers discovered a terrifying paradox: ... they had designed a product so good, it was destroying their own business.
The economic equation was simple: if a customer only needs to buy a lightbulb once in their lifetime, your market eventually shrinks to zero. ... As lightbulb durability climbed, sales plummeted worldwide. ... Factories began shutting down, and the titans of the lighting industry faced a catastrophic threat to their bottom line. The survival of their corporate empires depended on a radical, counter-intuitive shift: they had to stop engineering a better future, and start engineering artificial failure. In order to survive, they had to make their products worse.
On Christmas Eve in 1924, a secret alliance was born. ... The world's largest lighting companies—including General Electric, Germany’s Osram, Associated Electrical Industries of Britain, and Philips of the Netherlands—formed a global syndicate. ... They named it the Phoebus Cartel. Behind closed doors, they divided the world into exclusive territories, fixed prices, and united to control the global market. They had created the world’s first truly global cartel, and their primary target was the lifespan of the humble lightbulb.
The cartel’s first official decree was a brutal assault on engineering. ... They issued a strict, non-negotiable mandate: no standard lightbulb sold on Earth was allowed to last longer than 1,000 hours. This was a dramatic drop from the 2,500-hour standard of the era. Companies were ordered to redesign their bulbs, replacing durable materials with fragile tungsten filaments that would thin and snap after a set amount of time. Under the guise of standardization, the cartel had institutionalized a design defect.
To ensure compliance, the Phoebus Cartel acted like a private intelligence agency. ... They established a central testing laboratory in Geneva, where thousands of bulbs from member companies were constantly monitored and measured. ... If a member's bulb exceeded the 1,000-hour limit, the cartel imposed massive, crippling fines that could bankrupt a medium-sized manufacturer. For the first time in history, engineers were actively punished for creating a superior product. The pursuit of excellence was classified as a financial crime.
But how do you sell a deliberately worsened product to a skeptical public? ... The cartel launched a massive, coordinated propaganda campaign. They filled newspapers and billboards with deceptive advertisements, claiming that shorter-lasting bulbs were actually brighter, more efficient, and safer for the home. ... They convinced consumers that a lightbulb that burned out quickly was a sign of modern progress and high quality. The public believed the lie, sales rebounded, and the cartel's profits reached unprecedented heights.
For nearly fifteen years, the Phoebus Cartel held the world's electricity in a chokehold. But their shadow empire was ultimately shattered not by consumer outrage, but by global war. ... In 1939, the outbreak of World War II severed the international trade routes and alliances that held the cartel together. German, British, and American corporations suddenly found themselves on opposing sides of a deadly conflict. The secret syndicate officially dissolved, but the dark legacy they had pioneered was already deeply woven into the fabric of capitalism.
The Phoebus Cartel died, but the concept they invented survived and mutated. They had proven that the most profitable business model was not to make a product that lasts, but to make a product that must be constantly replaced. ... This strategy became known as planned obsolescence. Today, it is no longer a secret conspiracy; it is a standard business strategy taught in every major business school. It is the invisible force that drives the modern consumer economy, ensuring that factories never stop humming, and profits never stop growing.
Look around you today, and you will see the ghosts of that 1924 Geneva meeting everywhere. ... It is in the modern smartphone designed with a sealed, unreplaceable battery that degrades after two years. ... It is in the printer that displays a fatal error code and refuses to print, even though its mechanical parts are perfectly functional. We are surrounded by products engineered to die, trapped in a relentless loop of buying, discarding, and upgrading. The lightbulb cartel may be gone, but their shadow still controls everything we own.
They didn't just control the light; they programmed our dependency on the dark. ... The next time a device breaks in your hands, remember that it didn't fail by accident—it succeeded in doing exactly what its creators designed it to do. ... If you want to uncover the hidden histories and corporate conspiracies that shape our modern world, join us in the shadows. Subscribe to Corporate Shadows, and never look at the products you buy the same way again.