For fifty years, you were told that fat makes you fat. ... It was a lie. A lie bought and paid for by three Harvard scientists and a bag of cash.
The year is 1955. The President of the United States, Dwight D. Eisenhower, suffers a massive heart attack. ... Suddenly, America is terrified. Heart disease is skyrocketing, and the public demands a culprit.
Scientists were divided into two camps. British physiologist John Yudkin pointed his finger directly at sugar. ... But another man, Ancel Keys, insisted it was saturated fat. The battle lines were drawn.
The Sugar Research Foundation—a powerful lobbying arm—saw the threat. If Yudkin won, their empire would collapse. ... They couldn't let that happen. So, they launched a secret initiative: Project 226.
In 1965, a sugar executive named John Hickson reached out to top researchers at Harvard University. ... The offer? Fifty thousand dollars in today's money. The job? Write a review paper shifting all the blame to fat.
Led by Dr. Mark Hegsted, the Harvard team got to work. Hickson handpicked the studies they were allowed to use. ... Any research pointing to sugar was ruthlessly discredited.
In 1967, their findings were published in the prestigious New England Journal of Medicine. ... But they conveniently left out one tiny detail... who funded the research.
With Harvard's backing, the sugar industry unleashed a PR blitz. John Yudkin was destroyed. His book warning against sugar was mocked, his funding was cut, and his career ruined.
The world swallowed the lie. The government officially recommended a low-fat diet. ... But when food companies took the fat out, the food tasted like cardboard. Their solution? Pump it full of sugar.
As Americans ate less fat and more sugar, an unseen epidemic was born. ... Obesity and Type 2 Diabetes didn't go down. They skyrocketed to catastrophic levels.
The truth stayed buried for five decades. Until 2016, when a researcher dusting off old archives stumbled upon the original letters. ... The smoking gun of the Sugar Research Foundation.
Fifty thousand dollars. That's all it cost to rewrite scientific history. ... The sugar industry bought their innocence, and millions of people paid the price with their lives.