The question sounds almost severe: why are you writing such despondent letters? A softer teacher might have answered only with sympathy. Hegumen Nikon Vorobiev answered with something harder, and perhaps more merciful. He saw despondency not only as pain, but as a spiritual danger that could swallow prayer, hope, and truth. He was not mocking the wounded soul. He was refusing to let despair become the final word. In a letter to a spiritual daughter, he speaks like an elder who knows suffering from the inside, and who still insists that the soul must turn toward God.
Nikon's counsel should never be detached from his life. Born Nikolay Vorobiev in 1894, he searched through study, philosophy, and the modern intellectual world before finding faith through a deep crisis. He became a monk and priest in the Soviet period, was arrested in 1933, sentenced to a labor camp, and later served as a parish priest in hard years. So when he writes against despondency, he is not speaking from a protected room. He is speaking as someone who had seen ideals collapse, institutions turn cruel, and human strength prove terribly limited.
In Orthodox language, despondency is not simply sadness. It can become a temptation to abandon the struggle, to stop praying, to believe that God is absent, and to interpret every wound as proof that nothing can change. Nikon's letter meets that temptation directly. He does not tell the spiritual daughter to invent cheerful feelings. He calls her back to repentance, patience, remembrance of God, and the ordinary duties that keep a person from sinking into spiritual paralysis. His mercy is not sentimental because despair is not a small enemy.
One of the hidden dangers of despondency is that it speaks with false authority. The dark thought says: this is the truth about your life, this is the truth about God, this is the truth about your future. Nikon's counsel pushes back. A thought can feel powerful and still be false. A mood can feel total and still be temporary. The Christian does not have to obey every interior accusation. The soul must learn to bring thoughts into prayer, into confession, and into the light of Christ, where they can be tested.
Nikon does not deny suffering. What he resists is the way self-pity can turn suffering inward until the heart sees only itself. This is a difficult distinction. Real grief deserves compassion. Real illness deserves care. Real injustice must not be minimized. But self-pity can become a closed room where the soul repeats its own pain without bringing it to God. Nikon's answer is to reopen the room. Pray. Repent. Do what conscience requires. Accept the next duty. Do not let pain become an idol.
This is where Nikon's teaching becomes especially important. Repentance is often confused with hating oneself. But true repentance is the opposite of despair. Despair says: I am trapped in what I am. Repentance says: God can tell the truth about me and still save me. Despair turns the eyes inward until the soul suffocates. Repentance turns the face toward Christ. Nikon's letters return again and again to this sober hope. See your sins, yes. Do not defend the false self. But never make your sins larger than God's mercy.
For a despondent soul, large spiritual promises can feel impossible. Nikon's medicine is often smaller and stronger: endure, pray as you can, ask mercy, keep the commandments in the next situation, and refuse the imagination's collapse. The next small obedience matters. Getting up for prayer matters. Asking forgiveness matters. Finishing ordinary work matters. Going to confession matters. These are not heroic gestures, but they keep the soul connected to grace. Despondency wants everything to feel useless. Obedience quietly answers: this step is not useless.
A responsible reading of this letter must avoid easy promises. Nikon does not offer instant relief. Orthodox pastoral counsel is not a replacement for medical help, professional care, or immediate protection when someone is in danger. The point is not to shame a suffering person. The point is to keep suffering from becoming spiritual surrender. A person may need help from the Church, family, doctors, counselors, and trusted people. But within all of that, the heart still needs prayer, humility, patience, and hope in God.
Nikon can sound severe because he speaks to the part of the soul that wants to make peace with despair. A gentle lie would be easier to hear. But the elder is not interested in making despair comfortable. He wants the person to live. He wants prayer to return. He wants the heart to stop believing every accusation that passes through it. His severity is the severity of someone pulling a person back from an edge. It is not contempt. It is urgent love.
Hope, in Nikon's world, is not a personality trait. It is work. Sometimes it is quiet, unimpressive work. The soul chooses not to curse God. The soul chooses not to curse itself. The soul chooses to say the Jesus Prayer once more, to confess, to continue, to ask for help, to forgive where it can, and to wait where it cannot. This is not theatrical holiness. It is the hidden work by which a wounded person remains open to grace.
The reason Nikon's letters still matter is that they do not treat people as religious performers. They address wounded people: people who are ashamed, tired, angry, afraid, and tempted to give up. He does not tell them to become impressive. He tells them to become truthful before God. That truth includes sin, but it also includes mercy. It includes weakness, but it also includes grace. The letter to a spiritual daughter is a hard mercy because it refuses to let pain become a prison.
Hegumen Nikon died in 1963, but this question remains alive: why are you writing such despondent letters? Not because sorrow is forbidden, and not because suffering is unreal. The question remains because despair is never the truth of the Christian life. We can grieve, repent, ask for help, and still turn toward Christ. We can be weak and still pray. We can fall and still return. The Christian life does not ask us to pretend that the night is not dark. It asks us not to crown the darkness as lord.
For someone hearing this while tired, ashamed, or frightened, Nikon's counsel can be reduced to one faithful movement: do not agree with despair. Say one more prayer. Ask one more time for mercy. Reach for help without shame. Go to confession when you can. Do the next small duty. Refuse the thought that tells you God has abandoned you. The elder's hard mercy is not a rejection of the suffering soul. It is a hand held out to it. And if all you can do tonight is whisper the name of Christ, begin there, without drama and without shame. This is The Saints: stories of holiness, suffering, courage, and grace. This channel needs your support. Please subscribe, thank you for watching, and may God bless you.