For fifty years, you were told that fat makes you fat. ... That butter, red meat, and eggs were quietly killing you. That if you wanted to live, you had to cut out the fat. Governments told you. Doctors told you. The food pyramid told you. ... And you believed them. Your parents believed them. An entire civilization changed what it ate based on this single idea. ... It was a lie. A calculated, deliberate lie. A lie bought and paid for by three Harvard scientists, a bag of cash, and one of the most powerful food lobbies in American history.
The year is 1955. The President of the United States, Dwight D. Eisenhower, suffers a massive heart attack while playing golf in Colorado. ... The most powerful man in the world, felled in an instant. The news hits America like a thunderclap. If the President isn't safe, nobody is. ... And Eisenhower was not alone. Heart disease, once a rare condition, had quietly become the number one killer in America. Between 1930 and 1960, death rates from coronary heart disease had nearly doubled. Scientists, journalists, and the public all wanted the same answer: what is causing this? ... That question was worth a fortune to whoever could answer it first. And two men were about to go to war over it.
On one side stood John Yudkin. A British physiologist and nutritionist at the University of London, Yudkin had spent years studying the diets of populations around the world. His conclusion was clear and backed by data: refined sugar was the primary driver of heart disease, obesity, and metabolic illness. He published his findings, presented them at conferences, and built a growing body of evidence. ... On the other side stood Ancel Keys. An American physiologist from Minnesota with an aggressive personality and enormous ambition. Keys had conducted what he called the Seven Countries Study, which appeared to link saturated fat consumption to heart disease. The problem was that Keys had data from twenty-two countries available to him. ... He only published the seven that supported his conclusion. The ones that contradicted him were quietly set aside. But nobody knew that yet. Keys was charming, well-connected, and relentless. And he absolutely despised John Yudkin.
The Sugar Research Foundation, a powerful lobbying arm for the sugar industry, saw the threat immediately. If Yudkin won the argument, sugar would stop being treated as an innocent source of energy and start being treated as a suspect in America's biggest health crisis. That was not just a scientific problem. It was a business emergency. ... So instead of proving sugar was safe in an open debate, they chose a cleaner strategy: change the debate itself. Inside industry memos, the plan became known as Project 226. The goal was simple, cold, and devastating. Make fat look guilty, make sugar look irrelevant, and make sure the public never noticed who was standing behind the curtain.
In 1965, a sugar executive named John Hickson reached out to top researchers at Harvard University. The names mattered. Harvard carried authority. If the same argument came from an industry lobbyist, journalists might question it. If it came from Harvard scientists, it would sound like settled truth. ... The offer was about fifty thousand dollars in today's money. Not millions. Not a giant suitcase of cash. Just enough money to buy influence at exactly the right point in the scientific conversation. The job was not to discover the truth. The job was to write a review paper that shifted blame away from sugar and toward saturated fat. And Hickson did not hide what he wanted. He sent the researchers studies, suggested which evidence should matter, and made clear that the final paper needed to protect sugar from suspicion.
The methodology was designed to reach a predetermined answer. Hickson supplied the studies. Hegsted’s team reviewed them selectively. Studies that linked sugar to heart disease were dismissed as methodologically flawed. Studies that implicated fat were highlighted and endorsed. ... The result was not independent science. It was a performance of science. It used the language of peer review, the credentials of Harvard, and the format of academic literature to deliver a conclusion that had already been purchased. ... Meanwhile, Yudkin continued publishing real data. In 1972, he released his landmark book, Pure, White and Deadly, which laid out the entire case against sugar in plain terms. He warned that the sugar industry was manipulating research, that sugar was driving not just heart disease but diabetes, obesity, and liver damage. ... He was telling the truth. And the industry was ready for him.
In 1967, the Hegsted paper was published in two parts in the New England Journal of Medicine, one of the most respected medical publications in the world. The conclusion was unambiguous: dietary fat was the primary cause of coronary heart disease. Sugar was largely exonerated. ... The paper was immediately cited by other researchers, referenced by government bodies, and treated as authoritative. It gave scientific cover to every institution that wanted to blame fat. ... At no point did the paper disclose that the Sugar Research Foundation had funded the work, selected the studies for review, and corresponded directly with the authors about the conclusions. There was no conflict-of-interest disclosure because, at the time, journals did not require one. That oversight would cost millions of lives. ... The industry had bought a stamp of approval from one of the most trusted scientific institutions on earth. And it worked perfectly.
With Harvard’s paper as a weapon, the sugar industry turned on Yudkin with everything it had. The Sugar Association hired scientists to publicly attack his methodology. Industry-funded researchers wrote dismissive responses in journals. Ancel Keys, who had his own reasons to destroy Yudkin, called him a 'mountain of nonsense' and attacked him personally in print with a viciousness unusual even for academic disputes. ... The campaign worked. Pure, White and Deadly was buried. Reviewers mocked it. Yudkin’s funding dried up. His reputation was systematically dismantled by people with industry connections who portrayed him as an eccentric, an outlier, a crank. ... He died in 1995, largely discredited, his life’s work dismissed. The scientists who took the sugar money went on to distinguished careers. Hegsted later became head of nutrition at the United States Department of Agriculture, where he helped draft the very dietary guidelines that told America to eat less fat.
In 1980, the United States government published its first official Dietary Guidelines for Americans. The central message: reduce fat. Reduce saturated fat. Eat more carbohydrates. ... The food industry moved instantly. Every major manufacturer reformulated their products to be low-fat. Low-fat yogurt. Low-fat salad dressing. Low-fat cookies. Low-fat everything. The packaging screamed it. The advertising reinforced it. Millions of Americans genuinely believed they were making the healthy choice. ... But fat carries flavor. When you remove fat from food, it becomes unpalatable. So the food companies solved that problem the only way they knew how: they replaced the fat with sugar. High-fructose corn syrup. Refined cane sugar. Glucose, fructose, maltose — any sweetener that could mask the cardboard taste left behind. ... A typical low-fat yogurt in the 1980s contained more sugar per serving than a can of Coca-Cola. Nobody was told this. The label said low fat, and that was all that mattered.
Between 1980 and 2000, Americans followed the guidelines. Fat consumption dropped. Sugar consumption exploded. And the results were the opposite of everything they had been promised. ... Obesity rates, which had been relatively stable since the 1960s, began climbing steeply from 1980 onward. By the early 2000s, roughly one in three American adults was obese. Type 2 diabetes, once rare enough that doctors called it adult-onset diabetes because children almost never got it, became so common in children that they had to rename it. ... Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease, metabolic syndrome, insulin resistance — conditions that track almost directly with sugar consumption — became epidemic. Heart disease, the very condition the guidelines were supposed to prevent, did not meaningfully improve despite decades of fat reduction. ... The science had predicted exactly this outcome. Yudkin had predicted it. He had been destroyed for saying so.
The cover-up held for almost fifty years. Then, in 2016, a researcher named Cristin Kearns was going through old documents at the University of San Francisco’s archives. ... Buried in a collection of papers belonging to a deceased nutrition researcher, she found them. The original letters between John Hickson of the Sugar Research Foundation and Dr. Hegsted at Harvard. Drafts of the paper with handwritten notes. Payment records. Instructions about which studies to use and which to dismiss. The entire transaction, preserved in paper, sitting in a box in a university archive. ... Kearns and her colleagues published their findings in JAMA Internal Medicine. The paper sent a shock through the nutrition science world. Here, in black and white, was the evidence that the foundational research of the low-fat era had been purchased and directed by the sugar industry. ... The New York Times covered it. Other major outlets followed. And for a brief moment, the world was forced to reckon with what had happened.
Fifty thousand dollars. ... That is all it cost to rewrite the nutritional guidelines of the most powerful country on earth. To bury a scientist who was right. To corrupt the most prestigious university in the world. To send two generations down a path that made them sicker, heavier, and more dependent on a food system that was poisoning them for profit. ... Nobody went to prison. The Sugar Association issued a carefully worded statement acknowledging the funding but calling the science valid. Hegsted was long dead. Keys was long dead. Yudkin had been dead for twenty years before anyone formally vindicated him. ... Today, the sugar industry continues to fund research. The same playbook is still running: commissioning studies, selecting favorable data, discrediting inconvenient scientists. In beverages. In breakfast cereals. In children's food. The names have changed. The methods have not. ... The next time you pick up something labeled low fat, or heart healthy, or scientifically formulated, remember a quiet boardroom in 1964 where a man named Hickson decided that your health was worth less than his quarterly earnings. The truth is always in the fine print. This channel needs your support. Please subscribe, leave a word of appreciation for the author, and may God bless you.