Prayer to Saint Paisios Velichkovsky Pray slowly. Read with attention.
O Holy Father Paisios, you traveled from Russia to Mount Athos and Moldavia, searching for the lost treasures of spiritual wisdom. With great patience and labor, you
translated the writings of the holy fathers, bringing the light of the Philokalia to a world in need of guidance. Teach us to love the teachings of the Church and to study
them with reverence.
O master of prayer, you taught your disciples the ancient craft of the Jesus Prayer, urging them to repeat the holy Name of Jesus in their hearts with watchfulness and love.
Pray for us, whose minds are easily distracted and whose prayer life is weak. Help us to find quietness of heart and to remember the presence of God at all times.
O wise pastor, you gathered hundreds of brothers of different nations, building large communities in Neamț and Secu based on mutual love, obedience, and shared labor.
Intercede for our parishes, families, and communities, that we may be bound together in unity, peace, and brotherly support, casting out all gossip and division.
In our daily labors and studies, grant us your patience, Father Paisios. Help us to guard our minds from the noise of the world, to focus our attention on what is
pleasing to God, and to walk in humility and watchfulness.
Saint Paisios Velichkovsky, pray to God for us. Amen.