Prayer to Saint Nicholas of Myra Pray slowly. Read with attention.
O Holy Bishop Nicholas, who secretly threw bags of gold through the window of a desperate father to save his daughters from poverty and despair, look upon those in
financial distress today. Pray for all who struggle to feed their families, who are burdened by debt, or who cannot find work. Open the hearts of the wealthy to show
charity, and grant relief to those in desperate need.
O brave defender of the innocent, you personally grabbed the executioner's sword to save three men falsely accused of crimes. Intercede for all who face
injustice, corruption, or false accusation today. Protect the vulnerable from abuse of power, guide the minds of judges to seek true justice, and grant comfort to
those who are wrongly imprisoned or condemned.
O patron of travelers, who calmed the stormy seas and saved drowning sailors from shipwreck by your prayers, guard all who travel by land, sea, or air. Protect them from
accidents, natural disasters, and sudden dangers. Be a safe harbor for those lost in spiritual storms, and guide us all to the quiet shores of salvation.
Saint Nicholas of Myra, pray to God for us. Amen.