Prayer to Saint Herman of Alaska Pray slowly. Read with attention.
O Holy Father Herman, you left the peaceful lakes of Valaam to bring the light of the Gospel to the remote shores of Alaska. Embracing poverty and the harsh wilderness,
you became a father to the native people, defending them against greed and injustice, and teaching them the beauty of Christ's love.
O quiet elder, on Spruce Island you lived in a simple wooden cell, surrounded by the wild forest and the sea. You sought no earthly glory, finding your joy in constant
prayer and the company of the angels. Teach us to love silence, to find peace in times of isolation, and to see the beauty of God's creation.
We remember your boundless charity, O holy protector. When deadly diseases struck, you stayed by the sick, nursing them with your own hands. You gathered the orphans,
teaching them to praise God and caring for them as your own children. Look upon us today and protect our families and children from all harm.
We remember your inspiring words: 'From this day forth, from this hour, from this minute, let us love God above all, and do His holy will.' Help us, Father Herman, to
put these words into action, turning away from our old habits and dedicating our lives to the love of our Creator.
Saint Herman of Alaska, pray to God for us. Amen.