Prayer to Saint Sergius of Radonezh Pray slowly. Read with attention.
O Holy Father Sergius, you sought the quiet of the forest to devote your life entirely to God. Facing cold, hunger, and wild beasts, you worked with your own hands, building
a simple church in honor of the Holy Trinity. By your prayers, the wilderness became a spiritual garden, drawing disciples from all lands.
O wise patron, we remember how you struggled as a child to read and write, and how the Lord granted you the gift of understanding through the prayers of a holy monk. Look
upon students and all who face difficulties in learning. Intercede for them, that the Lord may open their minds to understand wisdom and use it for His glory.
O meek father, you refused all earthly honors and sought only the unity and peace of the land. In times of division and violence, you reconciled princes and brought peace
to divided communities. Pray for us, that the spirit of peace may dwell in our homes, churches, and nations, casting out all hatred and division.
Teach us, O holy abbot, the value of humility, labor, and spiritual watchfulness. Help us to guard our minds against pride, to accept our weaknesses with hope, and to walk in
the light of sincere repentance, always seeking the grace of the Holy Trinity.
Saint Sergius of Radonezh, pray to God for us. Amen.