Prayer to Saint Innocent of Alaska Pray slowly. Read with attention.
O Holy Father Innocent, you left the comforts of your homeland to carry the light of Christ to the cold lands of Alaska. Your heart burned with love for the people, and you
lived among them as a servant. Pray for us, dear saint, that our hearts may be filled with similar love for our neighbors. Give us the courage to witness to our faith through our
deeds, showing mercy and kindness to all we meet.
O tireless traveler, who crossed stormy seas in fragile kayaks and traversed frozen tundras in dog sleds, you trusted completely in God's protection. We pray for all
who travel by land, sea, or air. Grant them safety on their journeys, protect them from sudden dangers and storms, and bring them in peace and health to their destinations.
O wise educator, you mastered the languages of the people you served, translating the holy scriptures so they could read of God's love in their own tongues. You taught them
crafts, built schools, and guided the youth. Pray for all teachers, catechists, and translators. Grant us patience in our studies, clarity in our communication, and a heart
dedicated to serving the education of others.
Saint Innocent of Alaska, pray to God for us. Amen.