Prayer to Saint Paisios of Mount Athos Pray slowly. Read with attention.
O Holy Father Paisios, from your youth in Cappadocia and Konitsa, you desired only to serve Christ. In the quiet hermitages of Mount Athos and Sinai, you entered the arena of
prayer, fasting, and watchfulness. By embracing poverty, silence, and obedience, you conquered the passions and filled your heart with divine light, becoming a guide to a
generation searching for truth.
O wise elder, you taught us the beauty of 'philotimo'—that noble, grateful love that seeks only to please God and serve others without expecting reward. You urged us to
establish a 'factory of good thoughts' in our minds, transforming every difficulty and insult into a source of spiritual benefit. Help us, Father Paisios, to cast out
negative thinking, suspicion, and bitterness, and to see all things through the eyes of faith.
We turn to you in times of anxiety, panic, and distress. You who understood the heavy pressure of the modern world, pray that Christ may calm our restless hearts. Intercede
for our families, that peace and understanding may dwell in our homes, and that husband, wife, and children may be bound together in mutual respect and love.
O merciful father, you suffered patiently from cancer and bodily weaknesses in your latter years, never complaining, but offering your pain for the salvation of others.
Look upon those who are battling serious illnesses today. Pray to the Great Physician, Jesus Christ, to grant them strength, comfort, and, if it be His holy will, restoration
of health.
Saint Paisios of Mount Athos, pray to God for us. Amen.