Prayer to Saint Silouan the Athonite Pray slowly. Read with attention.
O Holy Father Silouan, you left your homeland for the Holy Mountain, seeking only the mercy of God. In the quiet of the monastery, you entered the difficult battle of
prayer, weeping for your sins and searching for the light of Christ. By your perseverance, you overcame the fire of temptations and became a vessel of divine peace.
O wise elder, in the depth of your struggle, when despair drew near, the Lord spoke to your heart: 'Keep your mind in hell, and despair not.' Teach us this great secret of
humility, that we may never trust in our own righteousness, yet never doubt the infinite mercy of God. Help us to guard our hearts from pride and to find peace in His love.
O compassionate father, you taught us that the true sign of the Holy Spirit's presence is the love of one's enemies. We confess that our hearts are narrow and easily filled
with resentment. Pray for us, that the Lord may soften our hearts, helping us to pray sincerely for those who oppose or offend us, and to wish for the salvation of all
people.
In times of depression, spiritual darkness, and dryness of soul, we turn to your intercession. When the light of faith seems dim, pray to Christ God that He may renew our
strength, grant us tears of repentance, and fill our hearts with the quiet joy of His presence.
Saint Silouan the Athonite, pray to God for us. Amen.