Prayer to the Venerable Elders of Optina Pray slowly. Read with attention.
O holy and venerable fathers of Optina, from Leonid to Nectarius, you shone as brilliant beacons of spiritual wisdom in a troubled world. In the quiet of your
monastery, you cultivated the fruits of the Spirit: humility, patience, and love. By your guidance, you restored countless souls to the path of salvation.
We remember your famous prayer for the beginning of the day, teaching us to face all that the day brings with peace of soul and the firm conviction that the holy will of God
governs all things. Teach us, O holy elders, to receive both joy and sorrow with thanksgiving, and to act in all circumstances with wisdom and charity.
O patient fathers, many of you suffered exile, imprisonment, and death for the sake of Christ in the days of persecution. Yet, your love did not fail. In our own times of
trial, conflict, and anxiety, pray that we may stand firm in the faith, bearing our crosses with patience and hope.
When we are confused, divided by social conflict, or burdened by mental heaviness, we ask for your intercession. Guide our steps in the way of repentance, help us to make
sincere confessions, and grant us that quietness of mind that comes from total trust in God.
Holy Elders of Optina, pray to God for us. Amen.