Prayer to Saint Ambrose of Optina Pray slowly. Read with attention.
O Holy Father Ambrose, from your youth you sought the narrow path of devotion, leaving behind the comforts of the world for the quiet refuge of Optina Pustyn. Under the
guidance of the holy elders Leonid and Macarius, you learned the difficult craft of humility, watchfulness, and prayer. In the quiet of the monastery, you fought
against the passions and became a dwelling place of the Holy Spirit.
O patient father, the Lord laid upon you the heavy cross of bodily infirmity, confining you to a bed of chronic pain and weakness. Yet, you did not murmur or lose hope.
Instead, you accepted your illness as a tool for purification, proving that strength is perfected in weakness. Through your suffering, your heart became a fountain of
boundless compassion for all who suffer in body and soul.
We remember your famous words, O wise teacher: 'Live without care, judge no one, vex no one, and pay honor to all.' Teach us, Father Ambrose, to put this simple yet
profound wisdom into practice. Help us to guard our tongues from gossip, to protect our minds from pride, and to treat every person we meet with love, reverence, and respect.
In times of grief, confusion, and daily discouragement, we turn to you for intercession. When our faith grows cold and our hearts are troubled by temptations, pray to
Christ God that He may grant us endurance and peace. Help us to find the right path in life, to forgive those who offend us, and to walk in the light of sincere repentance.
Saint Ambrose of Optina, pray to God for us. Amen.