Prayer to Saint Theophan the Recluse Pray slowly. Read with attention.
O Holy Bishop Theophan, you taught us that the essence of prayer is to stand before God with the mind in the heart, constantly remembering His presence. Pray for us, dear
father, that we may be delivered from wandering and distracted thoughts. Teach us to practice the memory of God throughout our busy days, holding fast to His name in
every circumstance.
O wise scribe of the Spirit, you spent your days in study and translation, sharing the deep treasures of Orthodox spirituality with the world through your letters
and books. Grant us the desire for spiritual learning and the wisdom to understand the teachings of the fathers. Guide our minds to seek truth, and preserve us from
intellectual pride and spiritual self-deception.
O quiet recluse, you found complete peace of soul behind closed doors, turning your small cell into a sanctuary of prayer and labor. When we feel lonely, isolated, or
forgotten by the world, help us to recognize these moments as invitations to closer union with God. Calm our anxious hearts, and fill our solitude with the
comforting presence of Christ.
Saint Theophan the Recluse, pray to God for us. Amen.