Prayer to Saint Seraphim of Sarov Pray slowly. Read with attention.
O Holy Father Seraphim, you taught us that the true purpose of the Christian life is the acquisition of the Holy Spirit. You counselled us to acquire a peaceful spirit, so
that thousands around us might find salvation. Pray for us, dear father, that our hearts may be cleansed of anger, anxiety, and judgment, and filled instead with the deep, quiet
peace that comes only from Christ God.
O patient intercessor, we remember how you stood for a thousand days and nights upon a stone in the forest, praying with uplifted hands for God's mercy. When our faith is
weak and we find it difficult to pray, grant us a portion of your spiritual strength. Help us to persevere in our prayers, to trust in God's mercy in times of darkness,
and to keep our eyes fixed on the Kingdom of Heaven.
O meek saint, you bore severe illness in your youth and physical disabilities in your later years with absolute patience and surrender to God's will. You did not seek
vengeance against those who physically harmed you, but forgave them completely. Help us to endure our physical weaknesses and bodily pain without complaining, and to
forgive from our hearts all who speak evil of us or cause us harm.
O bearer of paschal joy, who saw the light of the Resurrection in every person you met, cast away the darkness of despondency and sadness from our lives. Fill us with the
certainty of Christ's victory over death and despair. Pray that we may live each day in gratitude, greeting our neighbors with love, and seeing the image of God in every soul.
Saint Seraphim of Sarov, pray to God for us. Amen.