Prayer to Saint Nil Sorsky Pray slowly. Read with attention.
O Holy Father Nil, you rejected the ownership of vast lands and wealth, choosing instead to live in poverty and support yourself through the work of your hands. In a world
consumed by greed and the desire for more, pray that we may find contentment in simple things. Free our hearts from the love of money and possessions, and teach us to
trust in God's daily providence for our lives.
O teacher of watchfulness, you wrote deeply about the steps of temptation, showing how simple thoughts can grow into destructive passions. Grant us the grace of
spiritual sobriety. Help us to stand guard at the gates of our minds, to reject sinful suggestions at their first appearance, and to run immediately to Christ God for refuge
and strength when we are tempted.
O lover of silence and solitude, you withdrew into the quiet skete of the Sora River to practice the prayer of the heart without distraction. Teach us to find quietness amidst the
noise and busyness of our daily lives. Help us to quiet our tongues, to settle our anxious thoughts, and to listen in stillness for the gentle voice of the Holy Spirit.
Saint Nil Sorsky, pray to God for us. Amen.