Prayer to Saint Mary of Egypt Pray slowly. Read with attention.
O Holy Mother Mary, you spent seventeen years in the desert fighting the memory of your past sins and temptations as if fighting wild beasts. You suffered from
hunger, cold, and burning heat, yet you did not retreat. Pray for all who struggle with addictions, habits, and carnal passions today. When the memories of past sins
trouble us and tempt us to return to the dark, obtain for us the strength to stand firm.
O miracle of grace, who wept before the icon of the Mother of God and left everything behind to seek salvation in the wilderness, teach us the depth of true repentance.
Help us to see our own sins clearly and to turn away from them with a sincere heart. Pray that Christ God may break the chains of our habits and grant us the tears of repentance
that wash the soul clean.
O desert dweller, who was seen by the monk Zosimas walking across the waters of the Jordan and levitating in silent prayer, your heart was completely purified and filled with
the love of God. Pray that we may guard our eyes, our minds, and our senses from all that defiles the soul. Help us to seek the pure love of God above all earthly pleasures.
Saint Mary of Egypt, pray to God for us. Amen.